[clears throat]
>> Okay.
Uh everybody, the attendance poll is up
and it's 8:19.
>> [clears throat]
>> And [snorts]
uh
I'll wait about a minute. Okay.
So, today's lecture will be on
graph neural networks.
And uh yeah,
let's begin.
So, story so far
>> [sighs]
>> uh
we've seen MLPs
are
universal function approximators.
Can somebody tell me what we mean by
that?
What is a universal function
approximator? Somebody on Zoom, can you
check?
Yeah, they can model any function.
Excuse me, sir. Can you close your
laptop at the back?
You mind shutting your laptop?
Yes, thank you.
Right.
>> [snorts]
>> Let's go ahead. Yes.
So, it generally means that if we are
given any function
we can construct a neural network that
can
uh construct uh produce an arbitrary
approximation of the function.
And this can be trained through gradient
descent.
And uh it can be computed through
backpropagation.
So, we can see that
even if there is a one single hidden
layer, we can try to recognize the
pattern in data. And for example, here
it's a
uh digit trying to recognize a digit.
Uh
So, yes, uh that was the start of the
class and then we moved on to a bigger
problem of how to
uh design models for images, which are
basically two-dimensional in structure.
So,
uh we started scanning through these
images.
So, which is basically convolutioning
through them and learning those partial
patterns.
Uh and this was how we dealt with
dealing with
the two-dimensional data. And the
pooling layers reduce the spatial
dimension while we
>> [snorts]
>> uh
retain key features.
And again, uh this was trained uh can be
trained through variants of gradient
descent and we can be computed through
backpropagation.
Here's a little example of how we you
use CNN models to deal with uh
two-dimensional vectors.
Sorry, two-dimensional data.
And then we moved on to
sequence-to-sequence modeling.
Uh and we come across recurrent neural
networks, long short-term memories, and
finally the transformers. So,
uh where we used to encode input
sequence and decode the uh
the encoded sequence.
And the same procedure we try we can we
training through the variations of
gradient descent and we computed uh this
through backpropagation.
So,
yes, we saw a lot of
sequence-to-sequence models. Uh can
somebody give a few example of this
different types of sequence models that
we saw?
Many-to-one.
Anybody on Zoom?
Come on, guys. We've been through this.
So, can someone give us an example of
the first one?
Labeling an image. Labeling an image.
Okay. But what is a sequence? Where's
the image?
>> [snorts]
>> That would be a better example for
one-to-many. So, if you are given an
image, we can see it as a caption. Uh
so, that would be an example for
one-to-many.
So,
Mhm.
Yeah. Yes.
Maybe like reading a comment and seeing
if it's positive or negative. Sentiment
analysis. Right, perfect. Okay. Perfect.
>> What about the second one?
What? Give me an example.
We've been through this in class, guys.
This is really easy to
So,
>> [clears throat]
>> what's the idea? Translation.
No, the second one. Talk about it.
Oh, sorry.
Labeling an image. Labeling an image.
Okay. Image captioning. Yes.
What about the next one? Many-to-many
synchronous.
I spent a hell of a lot of time on this,
so you know, I feel personally injured
if you guys don't answer this.
Huh? What's
Come on.
We spent an entire lecture on it. Give
me an example.
We had machine translation on Zoom.
Yeah, machine translation at the bottom.
What is that?
That would be dealing with time series
data.
Can someone
You Those on Zoom, you're allowed to
cheat and go and look at the slides.
Those of you are not on Zoom, you're not
allowed to cheat.
Temperature forecast. No.
Temperature We gave stock market
analysis, part of speech tagging, where
you had to you know, for corresponding
to each input word, you had a you had a
class label
that
actually depended on the context, where
in the sentence it was.
Uh
things like that, right? Remember we
discussed this in class?
How long ago was that?
A month.
A month ago.
Bottom
left, right? Bottom right.
Translation. Translation. Which one is
that? Good.
Perfect.
So, yeah. So, we we dealt with all the
sequence-to-sequence models.
So, what was the main thing that we
learned on this particular modeling?
We
dealt with static data. We dealt with a
structured data.
That being said,
all of these models were able to do they
what they were done on the structured
and predicted data.
So, how do we go about representing
uh structure like this?
A molecule.
Um so, this has atoms and there are
bonds between those atoms, which
construct together to form a molecule.
It's a very complex structure.
How do we go about defining
or representing, to start with,
this particular social network?
Uh [laughter and snorts] it's a vast
network.
They could be, let's take this as an
example of people who are interested in
computer science. One group could be
interested in robotics. The other group
could be interested in computer vision.
How do we go about defining and
representing these relationships? It's a
vast
network.
So,
this is where the unstructured or the
dynamic data comes into picture. So, we
start dealing with more real-world
dynamic data compared to uh the
modelings that we were doing on the
static data.
So, that's why we come to
name them as graphs. And this is where
graphs matter.
So, again, to go about the real-world
applications and examples, a huge social
network. We can take an example of a
social media, Facebook. Uh there are a
lot of people and uh in it. And how do
we go about describing those
relationships from
person to person? Again, uh in our
previous example, a molecule. How do we
go about
representing these atoms and the
relationship between those atoms to form
a big entity of a molecule?
And uh traffic systems.
We can see that if a if one wants to go
from one point uh location to another
location, how do we go about uh having
the best route? If there is any traffic,
do we do a reroute to move on to uh get
to the location at a faster place?
So, these are
the real-world problems, where we deal
with more dynamic data.
And
to start with, let's represent this
particular uh again, taking our example
of a molecule, which has atoms. And
there are bonds between those atoms to
form a molecule. And
that's how we start representing these
nodes as atoms.
Or it can also be called as vertices.
And the relationship between those atoms
is called an edge.
Which defines the relationship between
an entity. So,
what is graph? So, I literally just said
Can somebody say that? Back.
Nodes and edges.
>> [laughter]
>> I did a summary, yes.
So, a graph is a general language on how
we describe and analyze
an entity and its relationship.
And that's how we see here, we have uh a
lot of atoms present in this particular
molecule. Which can be represented in
the form of nodes. And the relationship
or the bonds between these atoms can be
represented as an edge.
So, why do us as deep learners should
care about this particular thing?
Anybody?
Drug discovery.
What about graphs?
Yeah. Drug discovery.
That's one of the real-world
application, yes.
Like I mentioned, we deal with more
dynamic data in real world.
And they're more unstructured. They're
uh
This is what happens when we are in the
real world. Drug discovery, like you
mentioned. Yes, there could be a lot of
molecules that we don't know how they
are molecularly structured. What are
those properties? Is that particular
drug even safe?
So,
we come across these particular aspects
in real life.
Forecasting traffic, like I mentioned.
If there is a traffic in particular
destination, if you're trying to go to a
destination and there's a lot of
traffic, we try to reroute to a
different
uh look Sorry, different path to reach
that particular destination,
which is optimizing the problem. And uh
again,
more uh can somebody give me more
real-world examples
where we deal with more dynamic data?
Yes. Maybe a social network when a new
person enters in network, you can
recommend who could who could be a
friend, what posts they could like.
Correct. Uh that is an amazing example.
Another example, if you're trying to
watch uh pick a movie on Netflix, how do
we categorize that?
There are a lot of genres. Horror, uh
drama, romance.
So, all of this is how we structure in
the form of graphical representation.
And there is a poll.
815 816.
Perfect. 816 is not allowing me to vote.
Yeah, me neither. It is a second poll.
Okay, in case we can discuss it, right?
Okay, somebody on Zoom for the first
question.
Uh the Euclidean data refers to
data that lies in a space where the
distance between the points is
calculated using the Euclidean distance
formula. While the non-Euclidean data
involves spaces where the concepts of
distance may follow different rules,
such as hyperbolic or graph-based
distance. True or false?
True.
Correct. Uh
and somebody for the second question
here.
Second question. The CNNs and MLPs are
specifically designed to handle
non-Euclidean data, such as graphs and
hyperbolic spaces without any
modifications. Yes.
False.
Correct.
So,
the data that I mentioned, which is
static and dynamic, they're also
categorized as an Euclidean and
non-Euclidean data.
And while we are solving the graph
problem today, so the more dynamic they
are, we are dealing with more
non-Euclidean data.
So, what are the challenges that we come
across while we handle this graph data?
Like we mentioned, models like NLP,
CNNs, RNNs, which are more
uh which we deal on the assumption that
the data is more structured. It is more
regular. It's more fixed grid.
Uh but like I mentioned before, graphs
are irregular. They are unstructured.
They're more dynamic in nature. We deal
with more non-Euclidean data, which are
the real-world problems.
>> [clears throat]
>> And another problem that we see while we
handle graph data is that the graph lack
natural order. There is no
uh synchronous or there's no sequence
while we deal with graph problems.
And that makes them they uh the data as
permutationally invariant.
Uh so, for example, let's
uh take an example of a graph.
So, this is a simplest graph.
Uh and we can see that these are nodes.
And these are edges.
We can see that A is connected to B and
B is connected to C.
So, even if I change the order, if I
move uh A to here and C to, let's say,
uh here,
the they should be permutationally
invariant. They shouldn't change the
relationship that was predefined between
these two nodes.
So, even if I change the order, the
relationship or the edge
between these two entities should remain
the same.
So, that makes them graph as
permutationally invariant.
Uh and the standard models can easily be
incorporated
to uh for connective information.
And we need a mechanism to aggregate
these features from those neighboring
nodes.
So, these are the challenges that we
handle while we deal with the graph
data.
And there is an entire research
uh area dedicated to developing deep
learning models for dealing these
dynamic non-Euclidean data. And uh it's
often called as geometric deep learning.
So, before we dive in, let's start
with a little bit of a graph basic.
So, we can see here
a graph is an ordered pair of vertices
and
edges.
The entities and their relationships.
And
this is a
common structure or a example that we
take here of a complete graph. It has
four nodes, A, B, C, and D, and they are
edges between them.
How do we go about that in a matrix form
or a 2D format?
So,
we can see that we have an 2 cross 2
matrix, and
uh this particular
uh matrix shows if there is an edge or
if there is a relationship present
between two nodes.
Um so, we can see that the diagonal
matrix is all zero.
Why is that?
Why are all these zero?
Because a node is not connected to
itself via an edge.
Correct. So, we can see that there are
no
edge present between a self node. Hence,
all these are
zero in this particular diagonal matrix.
But, in our example, let's say we take
the similar example and
and we kind of have this particular
representation. Then, how do we
represent that in a form of a a 2D or in
a matrix?
For that particular example.
Yes. The one in the A spot. Correct. So,
then that kind of defines that there is
a self
uh relationship with
with that self node, and then we kind of
come across where we start representing
this as one because we see a
representation.
So, this is the basic way of how we
represent a graph and uh in its
topological way.
So, again, uh someone on Zoom perhaps.
So, why is this
particular
uh in the adjacency matrix zero?
Somebody on Zoom?
>> [snorts]
>> Anybody on Zoom? Why is the top left
corner of this matrix zero?
Anybody on Zoom?
I think the screen is not visible in the
Zoom at all. Oh, wait. Oh, they should
be able to see the screen.
You said no connections.
No connections. Exactly.
Should I log in on Zoom?
>> no. I think they can see it.
Oh.
Okay.
So, I assume they can see it. So,
anybody on Zoom can someone answer?
Oh, okay. Uh anyone in class?
I was saying there's no connection
between Oh, I thought there was no
connection on Zoom.
I think I apologize. Sorry, sorry, guys.
Uh
yeah. I thought I was not connected on
Zoom and they were not able to see the
screen.
Uh yes, that's correct. Uh sorry for
that. That was ridiculous. But, yes, uh
we can see that there is no connection
between B and B dash, and there is no
relationship, hence we represent that
particular representation as zero.
There are other form of representation
of how we can represent a graph.
Uh one way is called an edge list or an
edge matrix,
where we collect a a
collection of pairs, and there each
pairs indicates the that an edge uh is
connected between a node U and node V.
So, if we are trying to concentrate only
on a few vertices and edges, let's say
B, B and C or C C and D, we kind of form
a separate matrix on how we try to
represent them. So, that is basically
how we define an edge matrix or an edge
list, and we just went about how we
define an adjacency matrix.
So, moving on.
What are embeddings?
Can anybody say?
Let me throw it out because someone else
wants an embedding.
Anyone on Zoom?
Yeah. A higher dimensional
representation.
Correct. [clears throat]
So, an embedding is transforming complex
high-dimensional data into a dense
low-dimensional numerical vector that
our machine learning models can easily
process.
So, we went about a lot of examples in
the previous lectures. Uh for example,
let's take a word embedding, where we
convert the words into a vector such
that these words with similar semantic
meaning or they appear in a similar
context are positioned together in a
vector space,
from which these uh machine learning
models can understand how to process.
Uh the same goes with the image
embedding. We deal with an image data or
a 2D space.
Uh sorry, a two-dimensional data.
But, these are known and we have learned
this in class as well for structured
data,
what we have learned so far. So, how do
we go about capturing this for a graph
data?
Because we deal with a lot of
interconnectedness, there will be a lot
of complex relationships uh between
these entities or nodes. So, how do we
go about uh getting embeddings for this?
Anybody has a clue?
Well, let's see.
So,
basically, before
uh we start how to get uh an embedding
for a graph node, there are three main
aspects or how we include this in
getting an embedding for a graph. One
would be the node's own feature.
Two would be its local neighborhood. And
three would be the complete structural
role.
So,
we can see this in this particular
example. We have a karate graph, which
is quite a complex structure. And if we
go about representing this particular in
in in a graphical format, we can see
that they form these small clusters.
Uh and these clusters indicate they are
likely in the same close neighborhood.
And
that would be our second
uh way of defining this particular
problem. Uh the first one would be its
own feature. And the third one would be
the complete structural role, which
means uh in our example, which is then
karate graph.
So, that is how we go about how we
define to extract an embedding for a
graph graphical problem.
So, like I mentioned,
there are three ways of how we describe
a graphical learning task.
At the node level, which means how do we
define the node itself? What does it
entail? What does uh again, in our
example, this does this particular
person smoke? Yes or no? Or what this
particular node represents? At an edge
level prediction, we we come across uh
if we predict if this edge exists exists
and or if there is any definitive
relationship between two vertices. So,
again, uh there are two uh
There are two nodes, and there is an
edge present between them. So, what does
that particular edge represent? And at
the higher level of a graphical
structure, where we define what exactly
it is entitled for or uh if is this a
particular molecule structure or uh
like we mentioned in the real world
problems.
So, how do we do go about
in a typical format while we deal with
this
structured data? First, we create this
embedding and then we train this MLP on
this fixed embedding.
But, again, coming back to our graph
problem, we cannot go back because it is
not structured. It is very dynamic in
nature. So, we cannot flow back to
fine-tune embeddings that we have
generated in the process. And there are
other problems that we come across.
We have to retrain the entire embedding
space from scratch every time every new
node appears.
So, it's a completely different problem
on a higher level. So, and we have to
ignore or struggle to incorporate these
rich nodes, as well. So, the solution is
our graph neural network.
And there's another poll.
Okay.
So, true or false, the node embedding
aims to map nodes in a graph to a
continuous vector space while preserving
their structure and semantic properties.
True.
Correct.
So, coming down to our problem of how we
solve
>> look at the laptop.
Thank you.
The rules don't change halfway through
the class. They stay constant.
So, coming down to how we define this
particular problem, so we try to solve
them as graph neural networks.
So,
you can think that it's pretty complex.
I'll show you it's not. I'll walk you
through. So, what is a graph neural
network?
So, it is designed to handle this
irregular connectivity and the lack of
inherent order for nodes.
So, we can see this. Let's take this
example of a graph.
You can see that there is A, B, C, D, E,
F and
we want to
uh
Let's define our A node as our target
node.
So, there are three core mechanisms
which
is
our underlying
mechanism for the message passing.
Um and following
as gathering, aggregate, and update.
So, how do we go about defining these
particular mechanisms?
Uh and how is this message passing uh
process uh happen in a graphical
problem?
So,
one by one, let's solve it. So, gather.
So, our example here is a target node.
So, and there we can see that there are
three connections or edges present to B,
D, and C. So, AB, AD, and AC, which we
see it in this particular figure. So,
how does this actually
the process of message passing work?
The first thing, like I mentioned, is
gathering. So, the target node
looks at its immediate neighbors, which
is B, D, and C, and these
collect their own features
uh or their feature vectors.
And
so, these nodes start gathering their
own vector features, which is
an information, basically.
Right? And the next process of
aggregating. So,
um this particular model or this node
must take those multiple neighbors and
neighboring vectors and kind of squash
them into
fixed-length representation of what we
kind of see here.
And finally, this uh
combined
vector aggregation creates a summary of
what exactly the neighbors of the node A
looks like.
And this is what the aggregation uh
looks like altogether. And finally, the
update, where the node itself takes the
neighborhood summary and combines it
with its own previous state.
Uh and when we say that own previous
state, because A is also a node and it
has its own
uh vector features.
And so, it has to gather the neighboring
vector features,
aggregate them, and self-update to its
own vector feature.
That is how it kind of looks at its next
neighbors and what exactly uh is the
relationship or what exactly the
edge between them is defining. And that
is how the complete uh
mechanism of message passing looks like
in a graph problem.
Uh again, a little bit more math here.
So, the neighborhood N I of a node
I is defined as the set of nodes J
connected to I by an edge.
And for each sub-mechanisms of gather,
where each node will create a message uh
which will be sent to another node
later. And the aggregation, where the
node V will aggregate all the messages
from its neighborhood and combines them
into a single summary vector
HVL.
We can see that uh the aggregation of
all the neighboring nodes taking place.
And then finally, the node V combines
this aggregated message HVL with its own
feature vector from the previous layer,
which is the complete mechanism of how
the message passing takes place.
And this complete process is repeated
repeated L times to capture the feature
vectors from L-hop neighborhoods.
Again, a little bit of more
representation here. So, we can see here
we have two L-hop neighborhoods, where
this is a layer zero, and our start and
our layer Sorry, our
target node A. So, every uh nodes which
are forming an edge to the particular
uh node in the layer one will go through
the same mechanism of passing the
message from one
neighborhood to another neighborhood.
When we say a neighborhood, that would
be from one layer to another layer. So,
we can see that AC has
an edge for B
in the previous same example. Sorry,
there's no representation here. So,
you can see that AC
also Sorry.
Is that a different example? Yes.
Okay. Let's go with an example. We can
see that AC
will
gather, aggregate, and then pass the
message to B, which self-updates with
its own vector feature. And the same
goes with the C, where A, B, E, F all
gather and aggregate the information and
pass it down to C. And finally, and the
A to D, and there's a relationship. And
all this
neighborhood and then finally, B, C, D
goes through the same protocol of
gathering, aggregating, and finally uh
self-updating
uh the message message passing
mechanism.
And
to dive into a little bit more math, so
let's start with HV0, where it is the
zeroth layer, like in our previous
example. The zeroth layer uh
uh
Yes. Uh
and these layer embeddings are equal to
its own node features.
And we can see these two are the main
blocks, where we can see this is an
average of neighbor previous layer
embeddings. So, this is just an
aggregation function and we are using a
mean aggregation function, which
captures all the neighbors uh
Okay. We uh layers embeddings. And this
HVK would be the embedding of the uh
of V at that particular layer. So, if
you're dealing with in our previous
example, layer one, so the B will have
its own feature vectors, which is HVK.
And
uh the uh here we're dealing with an
aggregation function of a mean. So, it
would have gathered all the mean uh
embeddings of A and C
uh before it is added along with
uh
its own vector feature. And this is
passed through
uh number of layers, which is K, and
finally pass through our activation
function, and finally we
see that the message is completely
passed on to
our current layer, which would be the H
V at
Kth layer.
Any questions?
Yes. So, moving on.
Like I mentioned, we can define a lot of
different aggregation functions.
In our previous example, we have used
mean aggregation function with
normalization.
And there is an again summation
aggregation function. We can use max,
and there is min as well. So, basically
on how we are trying to approach the
problem.
And
uh,
as the previous example,
it propagates from one layer
down to its next nearest neighborhood,
and then so on and so forth until it
reaches its
final
Kth layer or our L-hop neighborhood. And
that is how the propagation of
information takes place in a graph.
So, a little more deviation on how we
train a GNN model. Let's take this
particular example of a node
classification problem.
We have this
very big structure of a graph, or let's
in our example a molecule or a drug. Is
this particular drug safe or not?
How do we go about training this
particular problem?
Let's say we are dealing with a
cross-entropy loss for a node
classification problem. In our example,
whether is this particular drug safe or
toxic?
Uh,
so we have
before we go about defining,
let's represent what exactly by these
notations mean.
These they are node class labels, which
basically represent each node in a
graph, and which are
these YV, and
there are the embeddings,
which
represent the
essence of
the node after it has gated information
from its neighbors, which is that VT,
and finally the weights theta, which are
the learnable parameters.
So, coming back to our node
classification problem, whether to
determine is this particular drug safe
or toxic,
there are two terms we can see here.
This is the first term, and this is the
second term.
So,
the first term only activates if there
is a true label one, which would entail
if this drug is safe.
And the second term,
uh,
activates only if the true label is
zero. That means it is toxic. If the
drug is toxic, this particular function
gets activated.
So,
uh,
the summation, which would give us the
final value if this particular drug is
safe or toxic, which is a classic node
classification problem in a graph
structure.
So, yes. Let's continue.
Uh,
so we dealt with a lot of representation
of graph.
So, there are
are two types of ways
on how we
uh, define a graph as well.
One, we can see that
it's a directed graph and an undirected
graph. Can somebody explain what is the
difference between the two?
Yes, please. In an undirected graph, the
edges go both ways. In a directed graph,
the edges usually only go one
Correct. In an undirected graph, it's
the relationship between the edges,
sorry, between the vertices is
bidirectional.
But in a directed graph, there's always
a direction present to what this
particular relationship between these
two nodes entitle.
So, we solved how we come across the
GNNs and how we kind of solve the
problem of a GNN. But are they enough?
So, this is one of the first papers on
GNNs, which
kind of seems very huge even for a
smaller problem.
It has barely, we can see that about
uh, nine nodes, sorry, maybe yeah, 10
nodes.
So, even for that particular small
structure, we come to see that it's a
really big problem.
So, achieving convergence
can take a significant variable number
of steps, and requires backpropagation
through a potentially very long sequence
of updates. So, it's very complex. So,
imagine we are dealing with, uh,
again, in our example, let's say New
York subway system. We all know how
chaotic that is, and it's so huge. So,
imagine dealing with such big problem.
If we're going to take, uh,
this particular complex issue, it's
going to be a much bigger problem to get
a solution for. So, how do we kind of
solve this particular problem? And this
can make our computation cost very
expensive and slow to train as well on
real-world large graph problems.
Wait, but are MLPs also kind of face the
similar issue?
So, what was the solution when we dealt
with MLP in this particular
and this particular issue?
Anybody?
Does it ring a bell?
It depends on the structure of the
problem.
Yes. We kind of
came across convolution, where
we literally used the problem
of extracting the local patterns,
where we used the filters to learn this
to recognize the features by looking at
a fixed local neighborhood of pixels.
So, we started sharing that
uh, space of information.
The same could be applied on graphs as
well. We could achieve this parameter
sharing. We can use the same filter
filter weights to, which is applied
across the entire image, making the
model highly efficient and scalable. And
this is also
uh, translation invariant or the shift
invariant because the model can
recognize the feature regardless of
where they appear,
uh, in the image. So, let's try applying
this particular logic on graphs to solve
the complexity issues that was faced
with the GNN,
which comes down to, uh,
the graph
convolutional networks.
And there is one big change. We can see
this this particular update rule,
uh, which makes, uh, us solve the
problems that were facing with the GNNs.
So,
again, the mechanism is still the
message passing or the propagation of
information.
And we can see this there is a
normalized adjacency matrix.
Uh, so
unlike the standard adjacency matrix
that we saw at the start of the class,
it is
normalized to ensure the nodes with the
many neighbors
don't overdominate the feature
representation.
And, uh, it essentially defines the
neighborhood from which we pull the
information.
Um, and there is an weight matrix, uh,
which is basically our learnable filter.
And just like a kernel in an image,
uh, we use the shared weights as an
optimize uh, during training to
transform this aggregated neighborhood
uh, features into useful
representations. And finally, an
activation function,
uh, to
uh, learn the complexity of the uh,
particular problem. So,
this kind of solves the problem what we
were facing in GNNs.
Uh, the GNNs were they were expensive,
and they kind of struggled to converge
on a larger real-world problem or data
sets, right? Um, so this particular uh,
solution solves the issue using the
first-order approximation
through shared weights, and basically,
uh, makes the GCNs much more faster and
scalable and powerful.
So, yes, like I mentioned, it solves the
problem of convergence and the
complexity issues that were
seen,
uh, in GNNs initially.
So, this particular, uh, variant is, uh,
derivative from the problem of how we
solve the GNNs.
Uh, and again, the old way where the
GNNs, we required all the nodes in the
graph to be presented during
uh training, and we had to learn their
embeddings, which was
not feasible in real-world application.
But, uh the GraphSage way,
we can see that there is a process of
inductive learning, which basically
suggests that instead of memorizing the
fixed vector for each node, we kind of
learn the aggregated function, which
allows us, uh the model, to generate
embeddings from the previously unseen
nodes by simply looking at their nearest
neighbors. So, just by looking at their
nearest neighbors, it kind of aggregates
the information what exactly these
particular neighbors would kind of have
uh underlying information, and which
makes it much more
uh
much more of a better solution compared
to what we kind of face
uh in the uh GNNs.
Uh for someone who prefers code, uh it's
uh these two aspects, which we really
define. Uh
it could be any aggregated function, but
coming back to what it really solves is
how we kind of uh squash a complete
neighborhood of vectors into a single
representation vector, and then uh for
every node, we kind of we look uh it at
its neighbors, and we kind of take all
their
uh hidden state from the previous
layers, and pass it through this
aggregated function, uh which gives us
the single vector that summarizes the
whole neighbor uh neighbors uh at this
particular stage. And finally, we
uh con- catenate uh these uh
features with its own uh vector
features, making it an updation
mechanism.
There's another poll.
Perfect. So, a graph neural network
using graph convolution can still be
trained for edge-level prediction, even
if there is no information in the nodes.
True or false?
Anybody on Zoom?
I heard someone say true.
Who was it?
Okay.
Anyway, but it is correct. It is true.
So, we look at the neighboring nodes,
right? So, we kind of get their hidden
state information, which we can
train
uh using convolution.
So,
what do you think we are kind of facing
as a problem uh with this particular
uh graphical convolutional network?
Can somebody think if there is any
problem with this particular network?
I mean, it's better than GNN, but still,
is there any problem that we see or come
across while we deal with GCNNs?
So, the standard GCN
kind of uses the predefined
uniform aggregation function. What does
that actually mean?
So, this means when the node receives
information from its neighbors, it it
kind of treats them equally.
So, what is the problem
uh if we are treating all the neighbors'
information equally?
Can somebody say, think, any guesses?
So,
if we don't, irrespective of their
importance
and feature relevance, there uh uh there
is kind of a flaw in just gathering the
mean of the information from its
neighbors.
So,
kind of we kind of need an attention
now, because
that
is a better solution
rather than just taking the mean of
uh what exactly the neighbors or
information from the neighboring nodes
is.
So,
this kind of comes down to uh
another architecture as graph attention
networks, where we solve all this
problem of having the mean uh or the
average of information that's been
derived from the local or the immediate
neighbors.
Um
So, yes, it's this particular structure
explains how the graph attention network
works.
Uh so, we uh have the linear
transformation, where we kind of apply
the shared weight matrix to every node,
and uh every node feature vectors, and
this kind of projects our data into a
higher-level feature space.
Uh
and by concatenating them, uh we can see
that uh it is transformed into a
transformation feature vector, where the
real attention now, uh attention
vectors, takes place. So, instead of
just getting the mean or average of the
information from its uh from our
neighboring nodes, we kind of pass
through
an attention mechanism, which again, uh
as same as the standard attention uh
mechanism uh for the sequence models as
well, where we kind of uh perform a dot
product to learn with this learnable
weights, uh
to get a result for a
much more robust way, rather than just
getting the mean or average, and
finally, passing through uh uh with
these attention weights passing through
the softmax, uh we kind of come across
all the neighboring nodes, and this
ensures that all the attention weights
kind of after we normalize with softmax,
uh makes it much more easy to interpret
the probabilities of uh
these particular
relative nodes and their importance.
So, training and optimization of a graph
attention network is again very similar
to what we come across with the sequence
models, but we will be dealing with the
problem
of layer depth. So, how many layers
uh is very identical for training. Uh
so, the study says it is two to four, or
keeping it as
reasonably low uh number of layers, uh
because there is a problem of
over-smoothing that we run into, which
I'll define in a little uh later. So,
coming back to it, uh everything else,
uh from pooling, batching, uh and
regularization,
uh the training and optimization of the
graph uh attention network is very
similar. But, the only constraint that
we come across is this layer depth uh or
the over-smoothing
at depth kind of a problem. So, what
exactly is this over-smoothing [snorts]
problem?
So,
the study shows that as we increase
layers, the node embeddings converge to
a similar value.
So, what do we mean by that?
So, the
deep uh
GNNs uh lose expressiveness. What do we
mean by this expressiveness? The nodes
become indistinguishable.
So, we can see that the there uh has
been study done on a small data set, a
medium data set, and a very large data
set across uh different formats of uh
graph neural networks. We can see
they've used graph convolution network,
graph attention network, and the
GraphSage. And uh
they when they started to increase the
number of layers across different
dimensional, sorry, across different
sizes of data sets, we can see that
there is a convergence issue. So, all
the different types of models of graphs,
as the number of layers increases, we
can see that, you know, after, let's
say, I think 8, 16, and if we increase
it down to 32, 64, or 128, we see this
hyperbolic convergence down.
Again, this not just in the small uh
data set, even on the medium data set,
or even as we scale to a bigger data
set, the problem is same. We see a
similar pattern, a similar uh again,
pattern of this particular convergence,
which loses its expressivity of what
exactly the problem it is trying to
solve.
So, this generalization was built on the
main hypothesis that while the nodes are
interacting, they have either access to
the important
information from the notes from the same
class or just noise. So,
by interacting with the notes and other
classes. So, we can see that as we kind
of
increase
the layers, we are apparently dealing
with more noise. So, this particular
layer is just a one layer that means
that it just has one straight
neighborhoods and there is very minimum
chance of
coming across a noise. But, as we
increase the layers to two layers, we
are susceptible for more noise. And this
is what is causing our over smoothing
problem at in graph neural networks.
Uh
there are more limitations. So, let's go
through it. So, like GCNs, the graph
attention network still operates on the
mix same mechanism of message passing
paradigm and it aggregates the
information from the nodes immediate
neighborhoods.
Uh and it calculates weight based on the
node features and local connectivity.
So, it really
doesn't include mean or an average of
information from its neighborhood and it
doesn't explicitly encode this full
position or structure relationship
between two nodes if they are very far
apart.
So, attention is calculated only on
subset of features on its neighbors. So,
limiting the complexity of this feature
interaction.
So, how do we go about capturing the
global parameters or long range
dependencies? Let's say at a very far
layer.
Which also leads to an over smoothing
problem. So, how do we come across
solving this particular thing?
So, turns out
we need transformers.
So, a little recap on transformers.
Uh
we just finished the lecture a few weeks
ago. So, but uh
a little
revision on that. So, we use self
attention which is to weigh the
importance of all the words in the
sequence while processing the new word.
So,
and these
attention scores are calculated using
the function query, key and value
which is typically scaled by a scale
dot product attention. And finally, the
feed forward network
which blocks the attention after the
attention mechanism to enhance the
expressiveness.
So,
these are the key mechanisms of the
transformer. And so, how how how do we
go about kind of
incorporating this particular uh
mechanism into a graph transformer?
Do we see any difference?
Yes, there are because we are dealing
with the dynamic data or the
non-Euclidean data, remember? So, the
difference arises when we need to adapt
the sequence based operations
of the original transformer to the
irregular, non-sequential, non-grid,
non-Euclidean
structure of a graph.
And the
attention scope, even though it's
customizable for the local attention or
the global attention, we come across
dealing with much more problem
we cannot use positional encoding or
where we because there is no sequence
order.
So, we cannot use any positional
encoding. So, we have to uh rely on a
much different way of how to incorporate
the graph structural encoding. And
there there are some other algorithms on
how we come across and solve this
particular problem. But, we can see that
it's is not as easy as just using the
same mechanisms that we can use it in a
sequence to sequence model or a
transformer can be similarly can be
similarly applica applicated to a graph
transformer.
So, this slide shows on how the graph
transformer and the information
propagation kind of structured.
So, we saw initially similar structure
of a graph where let's take this graph
in our example. We can see that A is
connected to B, A, C and D and there is
connection between B, E, C, F and
there's a C, G as well. And we can see
there are two nodes at far away which
are H and I which do not have any
relationship into this particular
graphical structure. That means we lose
the information of what these H and I
node is kind of
having and it's in own vector space.
So, this particular
thing is what we kind of started to look
at from the at the start of the class.
So, that's where the graph transformer
kind of comes into solving this
particular problem. The graph
transformer looks at the global
dependencies. So, even if they are far
away, even if they are not connected
into the graph
uh of the graphical structure, there we
kind of have
complete
attention that we maintain across the
complete global attention that we
maintain across the structure which kind
of helps us get the information from
this
H and I nodes even though they're not
connected to our particular graph.
Which helps us capture the long range or
the global dependencies of
graph.
So, yes, we can see
how
graph transformer kind of includes this
full attention and every node can attend
to every other node in a graph. So,
regardless of the distance and
regardless of the connectivity because
of the presence of the full
self attention. And we are
the problem of this particular thing
now, we kind of treat it as a
heterogeneous graph. And we kind of need
to
spot out the difference between these
edges because some of these edges, like
I mentioned before, they are not
connected uh
they do not maintain a relationship into
this particular graph. But, yet we want
to have the information or the hidden
states of those information of what
these particular nodes
possess.
Uh and the process is very similar to
the transformer architecture which is
represented here where we come across
uh
how we learn
the
message passing
uh paradigm into a graph transformer.
>> [clears throat]
>> So, yes, we learned a lot of different
models today. GNNs, GCNs and GAT and GT.
So, yeah.
Let's
you know
aggregate them. So, yeah, we saw graph
neural networks and how it had a few
problems leading to graph convolutional
networks
which again had a different set of
problems leading us to the graph
attention networks and finally, we saw
just a few seconds ago on how we
answer graph transformer.
So, the summary of how we started with
the graph neural network.
So, it follows the paradigm of message
passing or information propagation.
But, that is just a mechanism. It is not
a complete model yet. But, this is used
as a parent of all graph models because
that is based on how the message
passing paradigm works.
Uh and it had the complexity issues. It
was very expensive to compute. Hence, we
came across
graph convolutional network which were
computationally fast, but
it also had a con because it was taking
the average of the hidden states from
its neighboring nodes.
And even though that solved the problem
of GNNs,
uh but it was the con which basically is
taking the average and we do not require
that. But, it is still very useful for a
quick and efficient solution on a medium
size or a simple graph.
Which kind of led us to
graph attention
model which assigns different and
learnable importance scores to the
neighbors using attention weights.
Again,
even though the computing cost
increases, it is still limited to local
aggregation risk over smoothing.
Remember, as we increase the layers of
the graph, we need into a problem of the
over smoothing which
kind of is still a bigger problem. But
it was very useful to use on
very high
relation data. For example, a social
network or a knowledge graph.
Which led to finally our graph
transformer which learned this long
range
global dependencies
even though there was a previous over
smoothing problem. So this helped us
conquer the problem of no over smoothing
anymore.
And of course
as we increase down to the graph
transformer the competition cost
increases and we can see that the order
of
this particular
uh
graph transformer is or of n squared
because it has to every node has to
reach all the nodes present in the
particular graph irrespective of an edge
present. And it is very useful for long
range dependencies or a global
dependency and
Yes, even though they prioritize
explicitness over speed but it
definitely is more applicable for the
real world problems that we deal.
So
any questions?
Yes. Um so far we've only had
information in the notes. What if we
also care about information in the
edges?
Nothing really changes. I mean uh
The message passing can use information
from the nodes and from the edges. So
when you when you're gathering
information here
So the standard graph
neural network is looking at
unstructured graphs. If you just redraw
the graph doesn't change the graph.
That's why we have any permutation
invariance.
And [clears throat]
the way the nodes are each node has a
feature representing the node.
There are features potentially
representing the edges and there's a
feature representing the graph itself.
So when you process the graph each node
gathers information from all of its
neighbors
and then updates itself. In the process
of gathering information it can gather
information
not just about the neighboring node but
also the path that it took
to get from [clears throat] the node to
the current node.
So that's the basic idea of a graph
neural network.
The GCN says assumes ignores
edge features for the most bit. It just
averages the neighbors.
A graph transform
attention network
performs a weighted averaging.
It uses an attention framework to
compute uh
weights and then the graph transformer
looks at the entire graph and now in the
graph transformer because we're just
looking at the entire graph and where is
the graph? Everything is looking at
everything else. That information is
trans transferred to the positional
encoder.
So yes, [snorts]
how do we go about implementing these uh
uh ecosystems for GNNs? Uh there is a
PyTorch geometric library present which
is really industry standard and has a
lot of rich models and
uh ready production ready
framework. And there is another library
called as Deep Graph Library where it is
very framework agnostic
and it's also optimized for very large
graphs. And another library of NetworkX
where it is used for more of data
pre-processing
analyzing and visualization. Just to
give you guys a little bit of exposure.
Uh
so we see here
uh a knowledge graph
uh to give an example of how this
directed graph illustrates like a real
world problem and how does it solve
in this particular example of a person's
health
triage information.
So uh
we can see that a patient is admitted
let's say to a hospital
and as soon as he's admitted
the doctor or the whoever the physician
will
check for what his sickness or fever is.
And in order to incorporate or in order
to come to a justification he runs some
blood test which is another way of
confirming of what his sickness or fever
is. And this leads both leads to the
diagnostic
and saying that hey this particular
patient is suffering from pneumonia. In
order to reconfirm the diagnose they
send out let's say a chest x-ray to see
if there's pneumonia present in this
chest and finally after getting a
confirmation
of the edge
they
process the treatment for pneumonia and
finally which would lead to the roads of
recovery. So this is a pretty basic
structure of how a knowledge graph works
and uh
this is how we kind of
decode real world problems as well.
So going a little deeper
some of the topics that is very
essential for the
graph neural networks.
So we talked about expressivity. So
there is a test called as WL test which
kind of
uh
proves as the particular graph
very expressive in its way.
And it is a very iteration coloring
algorithm.
So how do we go about this? So initially
we start
by giving each node the same color.
You can see that
we started off in this particular top
graph at A.
We kind of give out the same color to
represent
all the nodes as indistinguishable. And
uh The next step would be aggregation
which from each node it looks at its
neighbors it collects their colors their
information and it also has its own self
feature vectors right? And it aggregates
that particular
neighboring information with its own
self
information and finally
this particular uh final map where it
shows that there are multi-sets. And
we can see that the result would be like
every node on how it interacted with its
neighboring nodes
was
identical at the start but finally at
the end stage we can see that because of
the information that has been passed
from its neighbors and its own self
feature vectors it has updated its
feature vectors to current present
structure.
And this kind of solves that how the
expressivity of a graph looks like.
And there is another small
topic of how we define equivariance
group.
Before we get into it what is an
equivariance? So
let's take an example of a molecule. So
let's say if if you rotate a molecule
and
it kind of predicts the force vectors it
should rotate by the same exact amount.
That is what equivariance means.
And the opposite of that would be
invariance which suggests that again
taking our
example of a molecule. So even if we
move the molecule or change the
structure it still remains the same
because it's scalar in nature. But
graphs are not scalar. They are very
dynamic they're not static hence we
define them into the equivariance group.
Uh
Like the start of the class where we
mentioned all graphs are permutationally
invariant this is the basic logic of how
the graph is structured. And so even if
we change the
indices of two nodes
it will still remain the same. And
it is how it is supposed to be
structured. And there are other
variance groups such as translation or
special orthogonal group where it
basically says that how and how much we
have
turned the
graph
and is this particularly tricky because
we are trying to rotate the graph or
move it into a different structure but
still the underlining logic seems
logic stays the same where even despite
changing or moving it it should still
remain the same molecule.
Which means that it's permutationally
invariant.
And finally
uh
uh these three equivariance groups where
the full set of special information is
kind of mode. It's like we kind of
translated and rotated and kind of also
reflected in this particular group. Uh,
but it still has to preserve the
distances and not necessarily change any
orientation.
Yes. Uh,
these are a few more equivalent and
geometric tricks for GNN.
So,
yes, finally, uh, a little more few more
concepts
before we end the class. Um,
so,
there are more generative models for
graphs. We can see that, uh, we have
progress from uh,
uh,
uh, different structure of VAE and
incorporation of a similar mechanism of
a VAE into a graphical problem. And it
is, uh, very useful for real-world
applications and especially in molecular
generation or a protein structure
decoding and in all these fields where
we kind of go through the generation
before we analyze, "Hey, is this
particular molecule or this is
particular protein uh, uh, exist in real
life and make some real-world uh,
implications.
So, yeah. So, the key takeaways,
uh, so, the underlying paradigm of a
graph is message passing or information
propagation, which is a universal
mechanism for graph and we structure,
uh, sorry, we studied the various
architectures starting from graph neural
networks to graph convolutional networks
from graph attention network and a graph
sage, which is a uh, another, uh, graph
convolutional network and finally, uh,
graph transformer
um,
uh, as well. And
the practicality of it, we have to we
saw the over-smoothing problem, hence,
uh,
in real world, we have to not uh, just
scale to a lot of numbers or layers,
which would kind of lead to the problem
of the convergence or over-smoothing.
So, we have to have this optimal number
of layers, which would help us really
get to where we actually desire in
solving a problem.
And we saw a couple of frontiers where
we learned about expressivity of a graph
and the geometric structure and, uh,
the generation or the generative models
for a graph as well.
And which is still, uh, very open
research.
Yes.
Um, thank you.
We have time for a couple of questions,
you guys.
Yeah.
Is there a potential to classify the
other graphs as ordered or unordered in
the future?
In the I mean, interpret. Yeah. So,
again, so, here's a quick summary of
what we covered. Do we have a chalk?
Chalk.
Yeah. Unlike images, you know,
standard data, you just have a data
point as a vector, you classify it.
Uh,
images, you have a grid. Your images are
always the same size. We rarely actually
work with images of different sizes.
And uh, although you could train an MLP
for the entire image, we scan for
patterns, right? Uh, time series, we
have time data coming in sequential.
They could be arbitrarily long. We
analyze those and we model them and, uh,
we uh, perform our inference on them.
A graph is an arbitrarily structured
thing.
Like
an image, you know, I could just draw
stuff of this kind, that's a graph. An
image is an instance of a graph where
all the elements are on a perfect grid.
They don't have to be Now, because
everything is on a perfect grid, you can
have this perfectly symmetric analysis
where your filter has the same set of
numbers, but there's a directionality to
the filter. You know, up is up, down is
down. They're going to have different
weights.
Left and right are going to have
different weights. But I have something
of this kind,
can we actually have
different weights in different
directions?
Can you do that? Is there a notion of a
direction in a graph? No, right? Because
I could just redraw this entire thing
like so.
Like
so, right?
And
this is still the same graph.
If you're
if you think about it, is that correct?
Yeah, right?
And so, there's no notion of
directionality over here. There's no
notion of, uh,
uh,
order,
which is why we want permutation
invariance. How are we going to perform
analysis on data of this kind? So, the
basic idea that people came up with is
that you can think of think of how
things connect to one another.
And so, you have a node.
This node gets information from all of
its neighbors. So, there's a two-step
process. The nodes are going to keep
updating themselves. Each so,
if you think of this as a neural
network, so, here's your graph. This is
layer one.
Then
layer two is the same thing.
Except now,
you know,
anytime you have connection of this
kind, you're going to have
connections of
this kind, right? This kind.
What's here is going to go here. You get
the idea. You just start loading the
graph over time, so to speak, and the
time is
goes ahead in layers. And
the manner in which you perform
inference is that at each time, each
each neuron, each node gets
ga- it gets the information from all of
its neighbors, does some magic on it,
comes up with a new representation. It
keeps repeating the process till things
saturate. That's the basic idea of a
graph neural network.
The problem is if you keep repeating
this in a naive manner, every eventually
every node is going to look the same
after a while because things just keep
flying over, right? And so, the basic
graph convolutional network
had this mechanism where it would just
gather
the information from all the neighbors,
average them,
they come up with an average
representation, you have your own
representation, you combine them
somehow, you're going to get a
uh, new representation for each node.
That was the GCN.
The problem is when it does so, it's not
really deciding or determining which
neighbor is more important than which.
So, what you can do is to use each
each node's representation,
compare the two and come up with a
notion of which which node is more
important and which is less. That's a
standard attention framework.
And then you get an attended
aggregation, weighted weighted pooling.
That was your graph attention graph
transformer, right?
And you still have a problem over here
in that path with few steps,
the thing is going to begin looking very
uniform.
So, if I have a deeper graph of this
kind, let's just say
a graph of this kind. This node has a
path all the way to here.
But for information from for going from
here to here is going to take four
steps. So, I'm going to need four layers
in the graph. The number of iterations
you're going to have to perform on the
graph will depend on the size of the
graph
for information from every node to get
to every every other node.
Is there a smarter way? That was the
final graph transformer.
So, in the standard graph transformer,
you just treat the whole thing as one
bundle.
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8. So, you have,
you know,
you have a collection of eight
nodes and when I update this node, this
guy looks at
all eight nodes. If each node is looking
at all eight nodes, where is the
structure of the graph? That is lost,
right?
But then it it's a shortcut. You're
getting information from everything all
at once.
You lost the structure of the graph. And
then they came up with a magic and then
the entire you transform the entire
problem to a secondary problem where you
capture the structure of the graph in
the positional encodings.
And so, the way the positional encodings
are derived, this node will have a
positional encoding.
This has its own positional encoding.
Compare these two positional encodings,
it somehow encapsulates all paths from
node A to node B
in a fixed manner. And now you transfer
the magic of graph processing into how
you derive these
positional encodings, which goes into,
you know, pure graph theory. So, those
are three basic those are the three
basic mechanisms that people use.
And now if you really want to look at,
you know,
do attention maps make sense?
Maybe they do, maybe they don't because
it's it's very hard to interpret. If I
give you a social network graph with
a billion people and a trillion edges,
how are you going to interpret anything,
right? Uh, then,
where is the, uh, structure of the
graph? Now, suddenly there's a lot of
external knowledge that goes in. How did
I design these positional encodings?
They have a standard techniques using
uh, spectral decomposition theory and
such like. And so, these things end up
being a lot more complex than your
standard networks because of the
structure of the data.
But for the same reason, they're also a
lot more powerful because at the end of
the day, everything is a graph.
Your image is a graph.
They're just, you know,
it's it's a graph laid like a grid. A
time series is a graph. It's just
sequentially laid. Your traffic is a
graph, you know, your stock market is a
graph. People sitting in this room, we
know each other, everything's a graph,
right? Your
your
homework assignments, a bunch of you sit
together, you are a graph.
Some of you are going to be doing a
better than the others, although all of
you are talking to one another. Every
last one of these things can be analyzed
provided you model it properly.
And so, [clears throat] you can see how
these things are probably the most
powerful
models, which is why I pushed it off to
the very end of course, but anyway.
So, let's stop here. Thank you.
>> [clears throat]